<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Anand</title>
    <description>Random articles on topics from programming to pink-floyd</description>
    <link>https://anandjoshi.me/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://anandjoshi.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 19:30:40 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 19:30:40 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Security Basics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been more than a year since I have written any new post, and I do have really good excuses, if I may say, to corroborate my claim, but that’s for another post! In this post, we will get a bit nerdy and revise some of the basics of security. You may use this as a quick guide or a crash course to recall these topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;topics&quot;&gt;Topics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#web-security&quot;&gt;Web Security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#encryption&quot;&gt;Encryption&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#message-authentication-codes&quot;&gt;Message Authentication Codes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#digital-signatures&quot;&gt;Digital Signatures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#digital-certificates&quot;&gt;Digital Certificates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-security&quot;&gt;Web Security&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When exchanging data over the web, the data passes through a number of networks and devices. Some of these channels might not be safe and might have malicious entities, hence security technology are essential for the safety of their users. Let’s look at the 4 prominent problems that can occur when data is transferred across the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1)&lt;/strong&gt; When Alice sends a message to Bob it can be intercepted by Eve
during the transmission. This is called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;interception&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/js/mermaid.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;
sequenceDiagram
    participant Alice
    participant Eve
    participant Bob
    
    Alice-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Eve: &quot;My bank details are xxx&quot;
    Note right of Alice: Sharing important &lt;br /&gt; details without &lt;br /&gt; encryption
    Note over Eve: Eavesdropper &lt;br /&gt; intercepting message
    Eve-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Bob: &quot;My bank details are xxx&quot;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2)&lt;/strong&gt; Even though Alice meant for the message to be sent to Bob, there is a chance that Eve was posing as Bob. Conversely, although Bob believes he received a message from Alice there’s a chance it was Eve posing as Alice. This is called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;spoofing&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/js/mermaid.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;
sequenceDiagram
    participant Bob
    participant Eve

    Bob-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Eve: Hello
    Eve-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Bob: Hello Bob, Alice here
    Note over Bob, Eve: Poor Bob thinks he is talking to Alice
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3)&lt;/strong&gt; Even if the message was transmitted by Alice to Bob, Eve could have overwritten the message during transmission. This is called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;falsification&lt;/code&gt;. In addition to intentional falsification by third parties, there’s also the chance the delivered message was corrupted by malfunctioning devices or channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/js/mermaid.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;
sequenceDiagram
    participant Alice
    participant Eve
    participant Bob
    
    Alice-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Eve: I love you &amp;lt;3
    Note over Eve: Message modified by &lt;br /&gt; malicious entity
    Eve-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Bob: I hate you !
    Bob-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Alice: I am breaking up with you !!
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4)&lt;/strong&gt; While Bob believes he received a message from Alice if the sender of the message Alice had some malicious intent there is a chance she might insist later that she did not send that message ! This problem is called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;repudiation&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/js/mermaid.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;
sequenceDiagram
    participant Alice
    participant Bob

    Alice-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Bob: I would like to order it...
    Note over Bob, Alice: Bob ships the items
    Bob-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Alice: Thanks. That will be $500
    Alice-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Bob: Sorry. I had not ordered anything
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These four problems are not limited to exchanges between people, but can also occur while browsing a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the ways in which we can address the above mentioned problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;No.&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Problem&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Solution&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Interception&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Encryption&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spoofing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Message Authentication Code or Digital Signatures&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Falsification&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Message Authentication Code or Digital Signatures&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Repudiation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Digital Signatures&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;digital certificate&lt;/code&gt; also helps to solve the inherent problem of not being able to verify the public key’s owner in digital signatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encryption&quot;&gt;Encryption&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encryption is the process of encoding a message or information in such a way that only authorized parties can access it and those who are not authorized cannot. In an encryption scheme, the intended information or message, referred to as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plaintext&lt;/code&gt;, is encrypted using an encryption algorithm – a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cipher&lt;/code&gt; – generating &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ciphertext&lt;/code&gt; that can be read only if decrypted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the types of encryption systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shared-Key Cryptosystem&lt;/strong&gt; : The sender and receiver use identical keys to encode and decde the message. Since the same key is used this type of system processes data much faster but the issue is how do we safely transfer this key. One way to do this is by using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diffie%E2%80%93Hellman_key_exchange&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Diffie–Hellman key exchange&lt;/a&gt; algorithm. Some examples - Caesar Cipher, AES, DES, OTP.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public-Key Cryptosystem&lt;/strong&gt; : It uses two different keys. The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;public key&lt;/code&gt; is used for encryption and the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;private key&lt;/code&gt; is used for decryption. It is easy to safely share the public key in this system however the data processing is a bit slow compared to the Shared-Key Cryptosystem. Some examples - RSA Encryption, Elliptic Curve Cryptography.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hybrid-Key Cryptosystem&lt;/strong&gt; : This system combines the above two systems to compensate for eachother’s drawbacks. Here we safely exchange a key over an insecure channel by using Public-Key Cryptosystem. After this all subsequent communication happens by using this exchanged key, just like in a Shared-Key Cryptosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the application of the above cryptography systems in my articles on &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/2017-12/Understanding-Bitcoin&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Blockchain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;message-authentication-codes&quot;&gt;Message Authentication Codes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Message Authentication Codes (MAC) are used to verify that the message received from the sender is not modified and is in-fact the original intended message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this mechanism both the sender and the receiver, use a shared secret key. This key is not known to anyone else [Similar to Shared-Key Cryptosystem]. While sending the message the sender calculates the hash of the message using the secret key, this generated code or checksum value is called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MAC&lt;/code&gt;. The sender sends this MAC along with the original message. The receiver on receiving the message calculates the MAC again from the message and compares it with the MAC sent by the sender. If the MACs are different than the message is discarded and not trusted. Since the key is secret, the interceptor can not modify and correctly generate the MAC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/js/mermaid.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;
sequenceDiagram
    participant Alice
    participant Eve
    participant Bob

    Note over Alice: Message (m1)=&lt;br /&gt;&quot;Contract conditions &lt;br /&gt; are xyz...&quot;
    Note over Alice: MAC (mac1) = &lt;br /&gt;h(m1,secret-key)   
    Alice-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Eve: m1+mac1
    Note over Eve: Eve modifies the &lt;br /&gt; message, but could&lt;br /&gt;not generate mac
    Note over Eve: m2 = Contract &lt;br /&gt; conditions are abc...
    Eve-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Bob: m2+mac1
    Note over Bob: Mac (mac2) = &lt;br /&gt;h(m2, secret-key)
    Note over Bob, Alice: mac1 != mac2. Maybe someone has changed the contract details !
    Bob-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Alice: Send the details again !
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above discussed method is called Hashed based message authentication code or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;HMAC&lt;/code&gt;. An alternative to HMAC could be &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CMAC&lt;/code&gt; which is Cipher based message authentication code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;digital-signatures&quot;&gt;Digital Signatures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A digital signature system guarantees non-repudiation in addition to authentication and falsification
detection, the two functions implemented by message authentication codes. It uses public key cryptography to generate a signature. The process is quite similar to HMAC as described above. The MAC generated is encrypted by the private key of the sender. The receiver will calculate the MAC from the received message and compare it by decrypting the MAC. The decryption is done using the sender’s public key. The encrypted MAC can be used as a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Digital Signature&lt;/code&gt; of the sender. However, there is one problem with this. How do we ensure that the public key of the sender is indeed the one claimed by the sender ? This is solved by &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Digital Certificate&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/js/mermaid.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;
graph TD
    h[\Hash Fn/]
    m[Message]
    mac{MAC}
    pri_key&amp;gt;Private Key]
    ds(Digital Signature)
    sk&amp;gt;Shared Secret Key]

    sk -.-&amp;gt; h
    m -.-&amp;gt;  h --&amp;gt; |Generate mac|mac
    pri_key -.-&amp;gt; |encrypt mac|mac --&amp;gt; ds
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;digital-certificates&quot;&gt;Digital Certificates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Digital Certificate&lt;/code&gt; we can guarantee who the creator of the public key is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A digital certificate contains public key, registered user details, email address, website or domain information. This certificate is issued by a recognized third party usually called CA or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Certification Authority&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The certificate authority has their own public keys and secret keys that they generate themselves. If Alice wants her digital certificate, she prepares her personal information including her public key and sends it to a CA. The CA after confirmation of the details use their secret key to sign or create a digital signature from Alice’s data. The digital signature and the user data is combined into a file and sent to Alice. This becomes Alice’s digital certificate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/js/mermaid.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;
sequenceDiagram
    participant Alice
    participant Certificate Authority

    Note over Alice: Prepare details &lt;br /&gt; public key, email, &lt;br /&gt; domain details ... 
    Alice-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Certificate Authority: Send personal details
    Note over Certificate Authority: Verify the details
    Note over Certificate Authority: Sign the details
    Certificate Authority-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Alice: Send back Digital Certificate

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if anyone wants to interact with Alice they would first request her Digital Certificate. Then they would acquire CA’s public key to verify the signature. This way we can be sure about the identity of Alice. Once the identity is confirmed the user can use Alice’s public key to securely communicate with Alice using &lt;a href=&quot;#encryption&quot;&gt;Hybrid Cryptosystem&lt;/a&gt; as described earlier. This is how the SSL certificates work. Instead of a person Alice, it is the website and your browser does the work of verifying the certificate with CAs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/js/mermaid.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

sequenceDiagram
    participant somewebsite.com
    participant Bob
    participant Certificate Authority

   Bob-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;somewebsite.com: 1. Requests for SSL Certificate
   somewebsite.com-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Bob: 2. Sends SSL Certificate
   Bob-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Certificate Authority: 3. Requests CAs public key
   Certificate Authority-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Bob: 4. Sends public key
   Note over Bob: 5. Verifies signature
   Note over Bob: 6. On successful &lt;br /&gt; verification uses &lt;br /&gt; public key of website &lt;br /&gt; to share secret key
   Bob-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;somewebsite.com: 7. Sends secret shared key
   Note over somewebsite.com, Bob: 8. Use this shared key for secure &lt;br /&gt; communication 

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;Hope this gives you some more idea about how cryptography is used for web security. Let me know your thoughts and suggestions in the comment section below.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2019-12/Security-Basics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2019-12/Security-Basics</guid>
        
        <category>geek</category>
        
        <category>security</category>
        
        <category>cryptography</category>
        
        
        <category>geek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Blockchain -  The Internet Of Trust</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Well, I told you, it was a bubble…” You must have heard many people say this after the epic fall of the bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies in the past year. Yeah, sure it was a bubble but we are not going to talk about that, instead, we would be focusing on the core technology - Blockchain and its applications in many other domains other than cryptocurrencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is funny to see how people overestimate what a technology can do in a couple of years and underestimate what it can in a decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/2017-12/Understanding-Bitcoin&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt; we learned about the inner workings of the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bitcoin&lt;/code&gt;. We learned that blockchain is essentially a distributed, an open-ended [free for users to join or leave the network at will], non-mutable [can not be changed once agreeded] ledger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bitcoin blockchain ledger contains transaction entries, but what stops anyone from creating another blockchain where instead of the coins and transaction entries in the ledger, some other data is stored. It could be used to build a robust distributed database in which anyone could write and read and the integrity of the data is protected in a similar way as the bitcoin’s protocol works. This opens up a whole new world of opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A database that is shared by multiple writers who don’t entirely trust each other, who modify that database directly and where there is some interaction between the transactions created by these writers.” - Gideon Greenspan [Founder of multichain]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you understand the above definition of a blockchain clearly then you have certainly understood where a blockchain would be useful and where it would be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.multichain.com/blog/2015/11/avoiding-pointless-blockchain-project/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pointless&lt;/a&gt; to use a blockchain instead of the existing solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2018/do-you-need-blockchain.png&quot; alt=&quot;do-you-need-blockchain&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So next time your manager barges in and talks about doing this new project using blockchain, please sit with him and ask him what exactly is he trying to solve? How exactly a blockchain will be useful when a traditional database which is much faster and scalable can do the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2018/blockchain-joke.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;blockchain-joke&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;alternate-blockchains-and-their-use-cases--&quot;&gt;Alternate blockchains and their use cases -&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ethereum.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ethereum -&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Technology to build decentralised applications. Bitcoin also provides a simple stack-based &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Script&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;scripting language&lt;/a&gt; to write some simple contracts like an escrow using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Multisignature&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MultiSig&lt;/a&gt;. On the other hand, the ethereum blockchain provides a more robust and Turing complete language - Solidity to the developers working on ethereum blockchain which can be used to build more complex decentralized apps, smart contracts, tokens and more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ipfs.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IPFS -&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; What if instead of hosting your website/files on a server you could just host it on a peer to peer network powered by another blockchain. No government or authority would be able to bring down such a website!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://golem.network/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Golem -&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Share computation power. Build the world’s biggest supercomputer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-applications-of-a-blockchain&quot;&gt;Other applications of a blockchain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2018/Blockchain-Applications.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Blockchain-Applications&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problems-with-blockchain&quot;&gt;Problems with blockchain&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Proof of work&lt;/code&gt; consensus mechanism uses an immense amount of energy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increasing cost of mining fees.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slow when compared to traditional methods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2018/blockchain-slow-meme.png&quot; alt=&quot;blockchain-slow-meme&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-novel-ideas&quot;&gt;Other novel ideas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are various experimentation going on to reduce the energy wastage caused by the Proof of Work consensus algorithm. Alternate consensus algorithms like Proof of stake, Proof of Elapsed time etc are being tested out to see their viability over the existing mechanisms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An improvement over the blockchain latency is being tackled by new ideas which use completely different data structures other than “chain of blocks”. One such example is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hederahashgraph.com/&quot;&gt;HashGraph&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not all blockchains are public and open to all, some of them could be regulated and would require permission to join. Such blockchains could be used by Government, Private companies or group of companies requiring some shared data which should not be public, yet the members would like the power to be distributed amongst the participating members. Such private and hybrid blockchains are also coming up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next&quot;&gt;Next&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think by now you have enough background and motivation to understand what a blockchain is, what does it try to solve and what are its drawbacks and where can it truly add a value. Now enough of talking! In the next article, we will get our hands dirty on some real-world problem and create our very first blockchain application.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2018-09/Blockchain-The-Internet-of-Trust</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2018-09/Blockchain-The-Internet-of-Trust</guid>
        
        <category>geek</category>
        
        <category>bitcoin</category>
        
        <category>blockchain</category>
        
        <category>cryptocurrency</category>
        
        
        <category>geek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Understanding Bitcoin</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to part 2 of the article series exploring our monetary system, bitcoin, and blockchain. In the &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/2017-11/Decrypting-Crypto-Currencies&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;last article&lt;/a&gt; we learned about our monetary system and the problems associated with it. In this article, we will try to understand inner workings of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bitcoin&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;decentralised-system&quot;&gt;Decentralised system&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Tim Berners Lee invented the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;World Wide Web&lt;/code&gt;, he envisioned an open and connected world where anyone can simply start a server and share their content with the world. Nobody owns internet yet everybody is a part of it. The internet is one of the finest examples of a decentralized system. Though over years, there has been a massive concentration of the power and this is because these big giants like Amazon, Google, FaceBook etc provide ease and convenience through their services, luring people to route the world wide web through their systems. And we also see the problems with it - NSA spying on us by partnering with these big companies. Governments censoring internet etc. Going ahead we’ll see how a blockchain can help in redesigning the World Wide Web so that it truly becomes decentralized as it was intended to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A truly decentralized system is such a system that does not have any central authority. The system works by the interaction of the peers amongst themselves. People are free to join the system, they are also free to leave it if they wish so. It is very difficult to bring down such a system, because you don’t know who are the entities of this system. For example look at BitTorrent - it is a simple peer to peer file sharing protocol. No matter how hard governments try they will never be able to uproot it completely and on the other hand see how easy it was for the government to bring down a centralized - peer to peer file sharing system - Napster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/centralised-decentralised-distributed.png&quot; alt=&quot;centralised-decentralised-distributed&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now we can appreciate the tenacity of a decentralized system. But there are also some problems akin to such systems. Since there is no one really in charge of such a system, you could see some entities harming others, building their associates having common malicious intentions. And it is very difficult to keep a decentralized system healthy and free of malicious agents unless we don’t employ central authorities that guard the system against such agents. So we see, here we have a trade-off between the freedom of decentralized system and security of a centralized system. No matter that Google/Facebook/Microsoft do have control over our personal data, but they also try to prevent it from hackers and other malicious agents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now that you’re somewhat familiar with a decentralized system, let us try to understand what is Bitcoin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bitcoin&quot;&gt;Bitcoin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin is a digital cash/coin that is tracked by transaction entries in a ledger. Cool, that was simple. Umm.. so who is responsible for maintaining this ledger? -“Nobody”. In fact, no single person or a central authority maintains or controls it, but rather the users and the community as a whole maintain it. But now you may ask, how do you ensure that all the ledger entries are the same? What if some malicious users in the network enter wrong entries into the ledger or worst send same money to two users, i.e double spend. How can all the nodes in the network come to a consensus about an entry in a ledger. These are some tough challenges for a decentralized application and let us try to understand each one of them separately and see how Satoshi-San cleverly bootstrapped a decentralized coin which seemed impossible to solve at first glance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/centralized-and-distributed-ledger.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;centralized-and-distributed-ledger&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-does-it-work&quot;&gt;How does it work?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll break down this into small blocks and link them one by one [pun intended] to build our understanding of this system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://learncryptography.com/hash-functions/what-are-hash-functions&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hashes&lt;/a&gt; -  In math and computer science a hash is a one way function that takes any string, number, text or any digital piece of information, runs an algorithm and converts it into a unique and short representation of that digital information, called a hash. Another property of hash is such that if the input was to be changed even slightly then the resulting hash would be very different. Hence you could use the hash to ensure that the digital data that you have was not tampered with and if it was then the resulting hash would be different and you could identify it quickly. Also note that given a hash, it is impossible to find out what the original input was.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/hashing.png&quot; alt=&quot;hashing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public-key_cryptography&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Asymmetric cryptography&lt;/a&gt; - In an asymmetric cryptography, a user generates two keys - private key and public key. As the name suggests the private key is personal and not revealed to anyone whereas the public key can be freely shared with everyone. If a person wants to send any message/data he will sign it with his private key [think of this sign as a hash produced by taking the private key and the data/message as the input]. Asymmetric cryptography is such that, now anyone can verify that this data/message was really signed by that same person. If an intruder tries to change the signed copy of the data then the verification will fail and anyone reading this data/message will come to know this message has been tampered with.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Immutable ledgers - As described above bitcoin is nothing but a distributed ledger shared and updated by its users. The ledger is such that any entry written into it cannot be forged or edited. And of course by now you are smart enough to realize this verification would be possible by checking the hash. So what do these ledgers contain? It simply contains a message like “Mr. A sends x amount of coins to Ms. B” and it is digitally signed as explained above by Mr. A’s private key. Now anyone can verify this by checking it with Mr. A’s public key. Now rather than using Mr. A’s real name in the transaction, the transaction contains A’s public address which is his public key. Hence Bitcoin provides pseudo-anonymity. As far as you keep using random addresses for each transaction, no one will be able to identify you. Okay, now the list of such messages having transactions of the coins are called blocks. Each block is connected to a previous block of transactions through hashes such that if any one of the blocks is fudged then all the blocks before and including it gets a different resulting hash and this creates what is called a “fork” in the chain. Now bitcoin is designed such that whenever a fork happens all the nodes chose the chain having the largest number of blocks. Now you may ask, what if the malicious users start building a longer chain together? Yes, they can but bitcoin prevents this through &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Proof of Work&lt;/code&gt; which we’ll explore once we understand the consensus algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/asymmetric-cryptography.png&quot; alt=&quot;asymmetric-cryptography&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consensus - Now we come to the most important part of the bitcoin system. Consensus means an agreement of all the nodes that the ledger has same values. This is the heart of the bitcoin design as you see it has many challenges. Let us first list down the bitcoin consensus algorithm and then dive deeper into it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/blockchain-mining-consensus.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;blockchain-mining-consensus&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When any person exchanges bitcoin with another person they are broadcasted to all the nodes in the bitcoin network.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each node collects these new transactions into a block [currently block of size 1 MB].&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In each round, a random(we’ll get to this later) node gets to broadcast its block.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other nodes accept the block if all the transactions are valid [coin spending, valid signatures etc]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nodes express their acceptance of the block by including its hash in the next block that they create.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay. So this was fairly simple. Now let us check what a malicious node can do in such a system and how bitcoin prevents it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a. Steal other person’s coin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If someone tries to do that then they can not “sign” the block or use the coins as they do not have the “private key” as far as the private key is safe, there is no way to spend someone’s coin even if they are stolen! There are further methods like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shamir%27s_Secret_Sharing&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;secret sharing algorithm&lt;/a&gt; to make your keys more secure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b. Deny transaction to a person&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nodes are chosen randomly(more on it later). Hence in later rounds, an honest node will get that transaction and process it. So this too isn’t an issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c. Double spend the coins&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As described before in case of two or more versions of chains a &lt;strong&gt;fork&lt;/strong&gt; happens and bitcoin is programmed to automatically picks up the longest chain. As long as the honest members keep building the blocks it will be difficult for the malicious attackers to outpace and build a longer chain. The longer the chain gets the more trust it builds [we’ll see this how in a minute] and hence after receiving coins we wait for some more blocks to be added on top of our block to get a longer chain and more confidence that this transaction forms part of the universally agreed ledger or consensus chain. [Currently, we wait for 6 confirmations I,e wait for 6 more blocks to be added to the block before we sign the deal. 6 is just an accepted number, you could wait more or less number of transactions depending on the stake of the deal you’re doing it !]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/forking.png&quot; alt=&quot;blockchain-forking&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Forking in bitcoin blockchain&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;proof-of-work&quot;&gt;Proof of work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after understanding the basic mechanism of a blockchain the obvious questions in your mind would be, how does bitcoin ensure that the nodes remain honest? Bitcoin solves this problem by incentivizing the nodes that provide a correct and valid block. The node is rewarded by 12.5 BTC [currently] and is halved every 4 years. [Eventually becoming close to zero, but never really zero, and roughly having 21 million bitcoins by 2140] The second incentive is transaction fees. The node processing the transaction can levy certain transaction fee. This mechanism of incentives encourages nodes to remain honest and cooperate rather than cheat and destroy the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second question would be how can it ensure, some malicious nodes don’t just add number of blocks and build a longer chain to displace the honest and valid chain. Bitcoin solves this by making the process of block creation expensive for a node. Each node is given a mathematical puzzle - a hash puzzle that can only be solved by trying a very large number of random guesses. So at a given time, all the nodes in the bitcoin network are solving this puzzle and the node that gets the right answer wins and gets to include its block in the chain. This process is called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mining&lt;/code&gt; as the node is rewarded with fresh new coins for solving this puzzle. Okay so you get what mining is but still, you would be thinking, what is the real purpose of doing this? Yes, it indeed has a deeper implication for the security of the network. Mining is computationally expensive and non-deterministic hence the first problem it resolves is that no node can gain the monopoly in creating the next block and thus monopoly in earning the block reward. Second it prevents the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sybil_attack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sybil attack&lt;/a&gt;, that is a single adversary controlling multiple nodes. Adding more nodes entails buying expensive computers and processors and hence makes it unviable for the adversary. Now you can understand why it is expensive for an adversary to fork and build another longest chain. As long as 50% of the users are honest [they are lured to be through clever incentive mechanisms] you can be certain that blockchain is safe. Note that an adversary planning to do a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/1/51-attack.asp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;51% attack&lt;/a&gt; needs to amass computing power more than first 500 supercomputers in the world as of now. Going ahead as more and more nodes start linking to bitcoin network this will become even harder and virtually unhackable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question you might have is, as more and more nodes start mining, it should be easy and faster for the network to mine the coins. The current design of bitcoin system is such that the difficulty of the puzzle is parameterized. That means, currently it is programmed to re-calculate the difficulty of the puzzle in the entire bitcoin network every 2 weeks. So if more nodes join the network, then the difficulty also increases and vice-versa. This re-tuning of the difficulty ensures that the average block generation time is roughly 10 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let us summarise by watching this video which shows a live blockchain example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/_160oMzblY8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; gesture=&quot;media&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that you can understand how bitcoin works and appreciate how it presents to the world a financial instrument of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/f/freemarket.asp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;free market&lt;/a&gt;.Again if you feel like reading more then you should read the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitcoin.org/bitcoin.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;white paper&lt;/a&gt; authored by Satoshi Nakamoto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next&quot;&gt;Next&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next article, we will understand what are the issues currently faced by bitcoin blockchain. We’ll try and get a broader and wider application of the underlying technology used in bitcoin - &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;the blockchain&lt;/code&gt; and explore some interesting and disruptive applications of it outside the world of finance. We will also see what the future of cryptocurrencies would be like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;I hope this was helpful. I would be happy to take your questions/suggestions and feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2017-12/Understanding-Bitcoin</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2017-12/Understanding-Bitcoin</guid>
        
        <category>geek</category>
        
        <category>bitcoin</category>
        
        <category>blockchain</category>
        
        <category>cryptocurrency</category>
        
        
        <category>geek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Decrypting Crypto Currencies</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The year was &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2008&lt;/code&gt;. Millions of lives and trillions of dollars were at stake. An old man’s entire life savings, a young and hardworking couples’ new house, a young lad’s tuition expense and job prospects were all being devoured by the government. Poor suffered while the rich were being “bailed out”! The citizens of the so-called democratic nations were just another puppets dancing to the tunes of their masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Very few realize that the power to create money itself has effectively taken away any other democratic rights that we hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, one person [or a group of them] did realize this quite early and he [or they] provided a solution to snatch away this power from the government and give it to nobody or rather everybody. We call it Bitcoin/Cryptocurrency today and the person [or the group] is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitcoin.org/bitcoin.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Satoshi Nakamoto&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to this first article on &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Cryptocurrencies/Blockchain&lt;/code&gt;. I suppose you’re either an investor or a developer or simply both! In this first part, I would like to give some background about a very simple yet highly misunderstood concept - It’s called Money!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-brief-history-of-money&quot;&gt;A brief history of Money&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first form of transactions to ever happen weren’t done with Dollar, Sterling or Pound bills but probably with  bones, meat, leather, stones or grains. Barter system formed the very first concept of transactions in the human history. However, this was difficult as each person had to have a thing that the other person wanted and was ready to exchange for it. Such a system was not productive for a healthy development of the economy and hence there was a need for something that could store the value of a person’s hard work, something that had an economic and intrinsic value, something that could be easily exchanged, something that would be divisible and fungible so that it could be measured and traded as per one’s necessity. This is why we invented Money. A lot of contenders came and were overthrown, however, some of them persisted and are still valuable today - precious metals - Gold and Silver being the top of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold and Silver had all the above-mentioned properties and quickly became the common mode of transactions. However, it had one problem. Carrying too many Gold/Silver coins was not easy as they are dense and heavy metals. So people started handing it over to Goldsmiths who would store and protect gold in exchange for a promissory receipt [and ofcourse for some additional charge]. The convenience provided by this was immense. People did not have to worry about carrying heavy piles of coins nor worry about its security. Very soon, people started exchanging the receipts rather than actual Gold/Silver and this was the birth of “Paper-based money” and the first bankers - The Goldsmiths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These bankers soon realized that the amount of Gold withdrawn by their owner was very less compared to the amount of Gold that was deposited and people were really content with exchanging the “promissory receipts” as it was very much convenient. Seeing this they realized they could just make more receipts than the actual Gold that it has. It was a clever scheme to make them rich at the cost of others - i.e if there were 100 receipts earlier backing X amount of Gold then the price of Gold per unit would be 100/X, but now the Goldsmiths just printed fake promissory notes and insidiously injected into the economy. So technically the price of the Gold would be 200/X. I,e it has doubled too. Of course, it will happen very gradually as the fake notes would gain entry into the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/gold-coins.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First money&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the above story sounded a bit unrealistic then I would like you to try and find answers for these questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The paper notes that the Government/Central bank prints, is it backed by some real thing having intrinsic value? Who controls how much they can print?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why does the price of things having “real” value like Gold/Silver/Real estate, over long run keep rising? [Does it not sound familiar to the Goldsmith’s analogy ?]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why is there always an inflation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s banks work on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/f/fractionalreservebanking.asp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;fractional reserve system&lt;/a&gt;, which says that a bank can loan out certain times more than the actual cash that they have. As discussed above such a system is prone to abuse and would eventually collapse, sinking everyone else with it. The power to create value / to create “money” should not rest in the hands of few but in the hands of all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;decentralizing-power&quot;&gt;Decentralizing power&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you understand the problems faced by our monetary system and its source, the next obvious question would be - How can we ensure that the financial institutes, the government, and the central banks don’t abuse the powers vested upon them? One solution is to enforce a stringent monetary policy like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bretton_Woods_system&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“Bretton Woods System”&lt;/a&gt;, this part is easy but the difficult part is to ensure that this policy is strictly adhered to. Such regulations rely on trust and you see trust and faith are not absolute but rather quite floating these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/decentralize.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Power to all&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now coming to the last part of this post, what if I told you that we could have a system where nobody - be it Government, Central Bank, Big corporations - absolutely nobody can manipulate the monetary system. This system grows and develops by overall consensus of the society. It fosters trade, partnership and everything you could imagine in a regular world to be done without having to trust the other parties, without having the overhead of legal contracts and securities etc. The word trust is never used in this system as there is no need to trust any central authority! It might sound too good to be true, but don’t worry all of that will be clear in the &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/2017-12/Understanding-Bitcoin&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;second post&lt;/a&gt; where we get pretty technical and explore the fundamentals of the first cryptocurrency - Bitcoin and it’s underlying technology - blockchain!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you now have some understanding of how money works and would like to get an even deeper understanding of it then I would urge you to go and check out this video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/iFDe5kUUyT0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; gesture=&quot;media&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;The cryptocurrency market is under wild speculation now. This article is not aimed at providing any investment tips but rather understand the technology and its impact on the financial markets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2017-11/Decrypting-Crypto-Currencies</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2017-11/Decrypting-Crypto-Currencies</guid>
        
        <category>geek</category>
        
        <category>bitcoin</category>
        
        <category>blockchain</category>
        
        <category>cryptocurrency</category>
        
        
        <category>geek</category>
        
        <category>social</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Mountain and the river</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&quot;With the dawn of sun you may evaporate but your essence shall flow through my veins forever&quot;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pa I can’t sleep” came a timid voice from a curled up blanket. “Me too” replied Pa in his deep yet a soothing voice. The little two-legged creature sprang out of her bed, her
hair almost kissing the floor, and rushed to snuggle up in her pa’s lap. It was a very special bonding shared between this 80-year-old man and his 5-year-old granddaughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Let me tell you a beautiful story” - “a story” lit up her blue eyes! “Yes - a love story,” said
Pa in his husky voice. “But I don’t know what is love, Pa”. “Neither Did I..” chuckled the old man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He picked up his guitalele and started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/345773589&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am gonna tell you a story..&lt;br /&gt;
story of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mountain and a river&lt;/code&gt;..  &lt;br /&gt;
listen closely my daughter..&lt;br /&gt;
story of him and her..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;He was a boulder, taller than sky..&lt;br /&gt;
little did he move when the tide was high..&lt;br /&gt;
She was a river, narrow and shy..&lt;br /&gt;
gushing through the canyon as years passed by..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But Pa, how can river and Mountain come together ?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A thousand years passed by..&lt;br /&gt;
the river dried out and that’s when the mountain cried !&lt;br /&gt;
Now he misssed her..&lt;br /&gt;
Oh he wish, he had kissed her..&lt;br /&gt;
so he looked up into the sky..&lt;br /&gt;
and made a wish in his cry..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And then there were dark clouds and thundering !” Frightened, she covered her eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pa, continued..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It rained almost for a month. When the dark clouds cleared and the bright sun came,
there lay a beautiful blue lake in the crater up above the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;She filled his crater -  that river..&lt;br /&gt;
pouring herself from the skies..&lt;br /&gt;
living happily forever..&lt;br /&gt;
the mountain and river&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Aren’t you two sleeping now ??” - yelled the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lake&lt;/code&gt; from another room !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Dedicated to my river, now my lake &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-heart heart-icon&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2017-10/The-Mountain-and-the-river</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2017-10/The-Mountain-and-the-river</guid>
        
        <category>poem</category>
        
        <category>song</category>
        
        <category>story</category>
        
        <category>love</category>
        
        <category>mountain</category>
        
        <category>river</category>
        
        
        <category>poem</category>
        
        <category>song</category>
        
        <category>story</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Backpack &amp; Guitar</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&quot;A backpack and a guitar is all I need !&quot;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new year had just set in. Some were filled with a fresh hope of a new start while others were gulping down yet another cup of a black tea to sober down their inebriation. It had been a tough or if I could paraphrase - an adventurous year for me. A strange feeling - the one that lingers and echoes in you when the heart and the brain are having a tussle was constantly nagging me. Damn them - why can’t they call it a truce ? With this strange feeling, 2 bags and a one way ticket I left home on the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;5th of January 2017&lt;/code&gt; to the land of the rising sun - Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They said I was mad and I surely felt like one after just moving to Tokyo. It certainly isn’t amusing when you’re awaken early morning on your first day by an earthquake, your phone’s data card ditches you when you need it the most. You have to set up an apartment from scratch without having a friend or family to help you and best of all you can’t really communicate with anyone for you both don’t speak a common language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four months and two solo backpacking trips later, I can only say that whatever happened - &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;It happened for the best&lt;/code&gt;. So here’s a little song, straight from heart, played on a Yamaha GL1 - Guitalele. The song is called - &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/anand-joshi-5/backpacking-original&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Backpack &amp;amp; Guitar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/323741456&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lyrics&quot;&gt;Lyrics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I packed my bag and took my guitar, &lt;br /&gt;
old country roads and night shining with stars,&lt;br /&gt;
who wouldn’t know, the sweet smell of sunshine,&lt;br /&gt;
and I wouldn’t miss, miss my city life,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You need a break, a time for yourself ,&lt;br /&gt;
go and get out of your comfort zones,&lt;br /&gt;
it’s okay if you feel lost, It’ll be worth finding for,&lt;br /&gt;
there are somethings that travelling teaches - which ain’t there in any book,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;there won’t be a better time, now is always a better option,&lt;br /&gt;
don’t drench yourself, in a pond of regrets,&lt;br /&gt;
if it bothers much then take a leap of faith, nothing gained if nothing’s ventured,&lt;br /&gt;
You’ve got one life - so live it to its fullest !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-memories&quot;&gt;Some memories:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;(Scrolls horizontally)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/nagano.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Nagano - Snow Monkey Park&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

	&lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/izu-kogen.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Pacific View&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/nagano-ryoskipark.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Nagano - Ryo Ski Park&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/izu.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Izu - Road tripping&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/omuro.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Mount Omuro&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/ferry.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Ahoy Captain&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017/shimoda-view.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Shimoda&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;-- A Backpacker  &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-heart heart-icon&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2017-05/Backpack-and-guitar</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2017-05/Backpack-and-guitar</guid>
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
        <category>japan</category>
        
        <category>living alone</category>
        
        <category>backpacking</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
        <category>song</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Into the wild</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;&quot; Because all I will be is a memory someday &quot;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plan&quot;&gt;Plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;October 2015. Nariman Point, Mumbai&lt;/code&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Over fifteen months had passed since the college had last ended and the wild and free animals within us
were tamed and chained in the zoo, which otherwise is known as the corporate cubicle. It had been more than seven months since I had even talked to him, but then that’s how bros are. We don’t need to talk or meet more often. One meet is more than enough to plan a &lt;strong&gt;Legen&lt;/strong&gt; - wait for it -  …..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision was made just a few minutes after we met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2-3 Weeks off from work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some trek in Uttrakhand.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Backpacking North India.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Called up another bro, back in Chennai. Without any hesitation, he too was in. This was our first - Yes first trek ever in life. (Hadn’t even done the simple ones near Pune in Maharashtra). And here we were planning to trek in the Himalayas on our own! But then what else do you expect from emotionally charged bros who were meeting after ages?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stairways-to-heaven&quot;&gt;Stairways to Heaven&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bro from Chennai could not make it because of the floods and heavy rains in the East coast of India. It was a difficult decision for us as the most experienced guy in the gang had dropped out. The tickets were booked, parents flawlessly convinced and urge to break free from this mundane life that led us to Delhi via Duronto Express on the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;11th of December 2015&lt;/code&gt;. After reaching Delhi the following day, we quickly rushed to the cloak room on the railway station to get rid of our heavy trekking gears. The next train - Nanda Devi Express was due midnight and we had close to 6 hours to kill. We braced the streets of Delhi, walked up to Rashtrapati Bhavan from India Gate, ate chat, parathas, sweets, and cookies on the streets of Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;12th December 2015. 5:45AM.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The cold winds of North welcomed us as we walked out of the Dehradun railway station. We were looking for a ride to a small village called Purola, from where our trek guide would join us. With hardly any tourists or trekkers to share the ride, the cab seemed to be an expensive affair (~6000 INR). So, in the end, we decided to hop into the stingy state bus which took longer time but cost us little more than 450 bucks to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;10:30AM. Purola.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We picked up Prakash, at Purola and got into the only cheap option left to us - a private bus from Purola to the base camp, Sankri (located at 6000 feet in Govind National Park, Dehradun). Accustomed to Virar local in Mumbai, I was used to sharing my seat with people but this bus journey also taught me to share my seat with a GOAT! - Yes, a freaking Goat sat next to me for close to 5 hours!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sankri hosts as the base camp for many treks in the Govind National Park. Kedarkantha and Har-Ki-doon being the most famous ones. Legend says that the Pandavas walked on these very trails of Har-Ki-Doon to reach the heaven. Though it was only Yudhishthira and a dog that ascended to the door that leads to the heaven - &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swargarohini&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Swargrohini&lt;/a&gt;- A steep snow clad beauty that can be viewed from the top of Har-Ki-Doon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We being the devils weren’t looking to enter the Heaven but just enjoy the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WV3L8AF8-BY&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stairways which lead to the heaven&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-climb&quot;&gt;The Climb&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;13th December&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We started our trek from Taluka with Prakash and another solo trekker who became friends with us the other day. Shivering in the early cold weather, I had worn almost all the layers I had carried only to shed them off when my body started sweating just a few minutes into the trek! There were some very steep climbs but overall it was a pleasant and a leisurely hike. The solo trekker had some back pain and decided to return back to the base camp to avoid any further damage to his back. We reached, Prakash’s house in the small village of Osla at the height of 9000 feet and 14 Kms away from Taluka. It took us several sore muscles and an entire day to reach there. The village had an elusive charm. It looked timeless - as if it had been standing there for ages. Some say the villagers are the descendants of Kauravas. The ancient temple of Duryodhan still stands tall to corroborate this claim!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Har-Ki-Doon was still 12Km and 3000 feet hike from Osla. The weather had taken a turn for worse and villagers warned us not to trek in this weather. The inclement weather had forced several trekking groups with sophisticated gears than us to return back. We decided to leave things to fate and went into a deep slumber to rest our aching bodies. I woke up at midnight to answer the nature’s call. I walked out of the house in pitch darkness only to be lit up by the milky way! The uncanny silence and the chilling winds were both eerie and beautiful. For a moment, I forgot the purpose of my outdoor visit and just stared at this engulfing Sky - so humbling and so divine it was - words will fall short to describe that &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/2016-06/Nyctophile&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;feeling&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/into-the-wild.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Into the Wild&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;span style=&quot;float: left;&quot; class=&quot;image-credit&quot;&gt;A road less traveled&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;14th December. 10:30 AM&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indiahikes and other trekking groups usually take around 6 days to summit Har-Ki-Doon. With fewer resources and no luxury of snow tents or fuel, we had to shoot for Har-ki-Doon without any halts or night stays. We began pretty late, thanks to Wagle, who seemed to be constipated that day! We started to trek under the scorching sun and snow clad trails at around 10:30 AM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2-3 Kms into the trek, I was panting and seemed to be burned out. Every step seemed like a mile. We settled down at a deserted Dhaba, which is otherwise beaming with people in the summer. A call had to be made, if we wanted to return, it had to be now. With no medics, satellite phone or any means of help, it seemed obvious to respect the mountain and go back. It was a difficult choice to make but after some debate and discussion, we decided to just ascend for next 30 minutes, settle down there for some time, have lunch and return back to Osla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounded perfect, but little did we know what lie ahead of us. 20 minutes later came a steep and curved climb covered with fresh ice. Just narrow enough to allow one person, it was a 1000 feet fall into the chasm on the other side. With no crampons, ice axe or sturdy trekking poles, it seemed like a suicide plan. The weather had not only frozen our limbs but also our brains and we attempted this with a wooden stick and our guide’s help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phew, we survived and the view after the treacherous climb was so breathtaking that the adrenal rush in me told me to continue the trek even if I could barely walk - &lt;strong&gt;one inch at a time&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;14th December. 5:30 PM&lt;/code&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
 Days are shorter and even more so in the mountains. The plan to continue hiking was turning out to be a disaster. I was slowing down Wagle and Prakash, who were also carrying half of my luggage by now. Time was running out, any mishap here could be fatal. The sapped out mind and body also knew this and was already operating on its survival mode. With hand gloves lost and jackets stuffed inside the bag (had removed heavy jackets earlier as it was warm in the noon), the frigid winds were now chilling our bones. But there was not even time to be wasted in removing a jacket and another glove. Any further delay could cost us our life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;14th December. 6:30 PM&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 After 8 hours, 12 Kms and 3000 feet we reached Har-Ki-Doon ( at ~12,000 feet altitude) in near darkness. Prakash gathered some firewood and ice for cooking while Wagle and  I put our feet straight into a fire like a BBQ. The first-degree frostbites had made our fingers numb. The sweat in the socks was also frozen. We just kept quiet and stared at the fire while Prakash was melting some snow to cook maggie. It was the closest that we had come to death and this very feeling that we were alive was both satisfying and infuriating. After what seemed like an eternity, I broke the silence -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;” Don’t you think this would be a hell of a story for our grandkids someday? “&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-lost&quot;&gt;Getting Lost&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;15th December. 8:30 AM&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 If there was any wise decision we had made in the entire trek than it was the decision to descend down and not take rest at Har-ki-Doon. Just four hours after we left the place, we could see the very place we were taking selfies at, to be shrouded in the mist and snowfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;15th December. 1:30 PM&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 The descend was quick and less taxing. We met a young shepherd, barely 9-10 years old around 5 Kms away from Osla. Little concerned, we asked Prakash to talk to him, but the boy ensured us that he is fine and his father is on his way. Seeing another person after so many hours filled us with a hope that the home is not so far now. We kept our bags down and started taking selfies again. After what seemed like a long photoshoot we realized that the guide was not in the vicinity. We called for him, yelled only to hear our echoes back. Although we hadn’t eaten much our stomachs churned badly. This was no good place to get lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily we remembered the place we met the young Shepard. We went back looking for the boy and were lucky enough to find him at that very spot. He guided us down the hill where Prakash was waiting for us. Although it wasn’t far, it surely wasn’t an easy and obvious trail and with the loud river gushing by, it was next to impossible for him to hear our cry for help!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/getting-lost.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;getting lost&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We finally reached Osla by 3:30 PM. Called up our parents after 3 days into the wild. We were glad to hear that we were the first tourists who summited Har-ki-Doon that winter. Even the Indiahikes camp was canceled and rescheduled due to bad weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;down-and-alive&quot;&gt;Down and alive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;16th December. 3:45 PM&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 After another day of descending we finally reached Taluka by tea time! The heavy snowfall that had started at Har-ki-Dun had finally reached Taluka where I experienced my first ever snowfall. Saying that we were lucky would have been an understatement now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, forgot to mention we finally took a bath on this day after almost 5 days!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;backpacking&quot;&gt;Backpacking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;16-25th December&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 The journey didn’t end here. This was followed by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 Days exploring Dehradoon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Going half way to Mussoorie, just to have food at a restaurant having rating of 4.9/5.0 on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zomato.com/dehradun/orchard-rajpur&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Zomato&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Going to Rishikesh. Free fall from 300 feet height - Bungee jumping. (Still can’t forget how the guy butt-kicked Wagga)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Haridwar. Attended the vibrant Ganga Aarti there.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Checked in at a cheap hotel in Agra at 4:30 AM. Visited Taj Mahal after a nap. Got kicked out early morning,4:30 AM the next day, in this cold winter as the hotel had “24-hour check-in policy”. Now I know why they built a mental hospital in Agra.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finally back to Delhi. Visited the historical places and of course hogged on the street food of Chandni chowk!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-ive-learned-from-this-trip&quot;&gt;Things I’ve learned from this trip&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know there are people who would have more crazy stories and experiences to narrate but then I am not here to sell my story. I am here to just share an experience that has made me value so many little things in life which I used to take it for granted. It saddens me to see that the next generation would hardly even get a chance to see the true beauty of our nature, although I am sure what I saw was hardly a fraction of what it used to be some decades ago. It is up to us to preserve our mother earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting in a comfortable couch with every possible amenities a click away, we are cribbing for pointless things and there I saw people in the village of Osla, hiking for miles even in their illness to fetch water. Traveling and meeting people, hearing their stories has made me value my life more. I feel even more gratitude for things which I did not perceive, forget about appreciating it before!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember cursing myself when I was completely drained and exhausted, promising myself never to go for a trek again, and here I was six months later on another Himalayan trek with my Mom (again a first-time trekker !). I wonder at times why do I hate it but in the end, I end up loving it more than ever. That is when I remember that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;” We are animals in a true sense and the wild will always beckon us.  “&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;center&gt;To the animal within us &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-heart heart-icon&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; !&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-memories&quot;&gt;Some memories:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;(Scrolls horizontally)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/sankri.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;A view from the base camp at Sankri.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;


    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/pose.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Praise the lord&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;


    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/studs.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Red Fort&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/temple.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Temple of Duryodhan at Osla&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/swag.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;The view after the treacherous climb&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/waggaboy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Good Pet&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/goat-ride.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;The one with the goat&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/harkidoon.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Har-Ki-Doon !&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/ascend.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;One inch at a time&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/cookies.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Delhi street food&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/retards.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Retards in Agra&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/breaking-glass.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Breaking hotel glass on the last day of the trip&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;


    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/got-guts.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;You've got guts&quot; - certificate after the bungee jump&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;


    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/ganga.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Ganga Aarti&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;


    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/trails.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Making trails for others&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/into-the-wild.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;A road less traveled&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;


    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/Prakash-family.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Prakash and Family - a wonderful hosts :)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/lost.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Lost and into the wild &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/snow.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Trails of the first campers ;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/img/2016/bros.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Bros and their swag \m/&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still waiting? ………&lt;strong&gt;DARYYYYYYY&lt;/strong&gt; TRIP!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;Feel free to contact me if you are planning a trek to Har-ki-Doon and would like to know more about it.
Contact &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=100008402793074&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Prakash Rana&lt;/a&gt; if you’re looking for a personal guide. He conducts many other treks, some of them with his father too. Happy trekking and exploring :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2016-12/Into-the-Wild</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2016-12/Into-the-Wild</guid>
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        <category>backpacking</category>
        
        <category>har-ki-doon</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Time to Fly</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Forgive not becase they deserve forgiveness but because you deserve a peace of mind”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know things won’t be right at times, the people you treated so well, you gave all your heart  &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-heart heart-icon&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; and soul to won’t do right to you or worst strangle you, treat you like you’re some piece of a disposable bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every thought of it just fills you with anger and disgust. After all is this what you get for being so nice ? Is this what the world has to offer  for your love, your care, your honesty ? You start  to slip in this pit of darkness and wrath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know it will be freakin difficult to get out of it. You say you’re nice and genuinely a good person ? Can I hear that once again, you said: “A nice person” - then go and freakin prove that &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NOW&lt;/code&gt; ! It is so easy to love when things are right , it is so easy to be honest when you have nothing to lose , so easy to say you’re nice when you never got an opportunity to be bad. NOW is what matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might ask,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is life not fair to me ? Why did such things happen to me ? Why ? Now don’t sit and cry around like a baby. Life is and will be unfair. That’s why you have hands and some cripples don’t. You have a family while others don’t. That’s why you had an education and someone to look after you, food, shelter and proper meals, some people didn’t even get that ! STOP making this about YOU ! Accept it and move ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might ask,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it so easy to lie and not be honest ? Why is it so easy to hate and not love someone ? Why ? Because freakin losers and cowards choose the easy path. You are better than this. You - yes you. Look me straight into the eyes - I am talking to you. Tell me right here, right now. Repeat with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;” I will be nice not because I have to, but because I am. “&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;” I will forgive not because they deserve forgiveness, but because I deserve a peace of mind. “&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;” I am better than this and I deserve better. “&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s okay if others or that person thought of you as some peace of dirty rock, they haven’t seen the diamond in you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now go and shine, brighter than ever before. Forgive and forget. There shouldn’t be regrets. This has made you a better person if not a wiser and stronger one !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time to shrug that dust off your wings and it’s time to &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/2016-07/The-Flight&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;FLY&lt;/a&gt;  !&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2016-12/Time-to-fly</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2016-12/Time-to-fly</guid>
        
        <category>philosphy</category>
        
        <category>motivation</category>
        
        <category>forgiveness</category>
        
        
        <category>philosphy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Old Letter</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Do it and regret. Don’t do it and regret more !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s not working out, I think we should move on.” He knew Tanya and her idiosyncrasies. “I know 
she would be fine tomorrow morning” he reminded himself like he always did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like a weed clinging to a cracked wall, Raj was clinging on to his dying relationship.
And if you think this was not the end then perhaps you should know how he abandoned his startup only to realize
that the other co-founders made millions just by pushing a little harder than him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem was that he had risked it even more by playing it safe. He felt time slipping through his hands like a sand, but well isn’t time always slipping like  that ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as he was about to shred the offer to work with NatGeo - wild. He received an email dated : 23rd March 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.futureme.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;scheduled mail&lt;/a&gt; was written by a 16-year-old Raj, quite different than who he was now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To Myself,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sometimes we just need to hop into that car that passes by. Take a detour. Digress a little (or perhaps more ?). 
It is the journey that will be Worth telling your grandkids for nobody cares about the destination.
Don’t be scared. Well if you are then that’s a good thing. You’re challenging yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;You wouldn’t know if it was the right decision or not ? As a matter of fact, there is no right answer to it.
You , My friend, you are the one who has to make it right for what it’s all worth for.
As it is rightly said you cannot connect the dots going forward but only going backward.
So step away , move ahead and fill your heart and mind with that hope of connecting the dots in a story that will inspire generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;If it all ends well, you’ll have a hell of a story, if it doesn’t then the story isn’t over yet. 
I hope you live a life that you are proud of , it’s okay if the dots still don’t connect 
but you know what , I want, I want every single page of that book to be a thriller !&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So go and start scripting your story, before the ink gets dry !&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Good luck !&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;– Raj , 23rd March 2003&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tears rolled down the cheeks as he was intervened by his own past. In next five minutes, he dropped a resignation to his manager, something that he should have done 7 years ago. He called up Tanya to end the stagnant relationship, something that he should have done 4 years ago. And finally, he booked a single one-way ticket to Auckland, where his passion for wildlife beckons him ! - Something he could have only done by listening to his inner voice :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is funny to see what an &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;old letter&lt;/code&gt; can do in five minutes, what a person could not in a decade’s worth of time !&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2016-11/An-Old-Letter</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2016-11/An-Old-Letter</guid>
        
        <category>motivation</category>
        
        <category>story</category>
        
        
        <category>story</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>URL Shortening</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;url-shorteners-&quot;&gt;URL Shorteners :&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, so you are tweeting about this amazing video which you think would be a big hit on the social media.
You open your twitter account, copy the URL and paste it to tweet, but wait ! The URL itself is 140+ characters, let alone your quirky comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then you hear about these amazing tools called - URL Shorteners. They convert the dirty looking urls into short, sweet and slick urls, which can not only be easily shared on twitter and other media but they also provide you a hell lot of analytics and user information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here are some commonly used URL shorteners :&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bitly.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;bit.ly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;goo.gl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ow.ly/url/shorten-url&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ow.ly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;well-but-how-does-url-shortening-work-&quot;&gt;Well, but how does URL shortening work ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/url-short.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;url-shortening&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us paraphrase what URL shortening tools do. They convert a long arbitrary length of string into a short and compact combination of characters, which has much smaller length than the original URL. So if we understand this, we
also understand that essentially these tools are just mapping one set to another, but where one set is very large, probably infinite where as the other is a smaller and finite set. Does this sound a bit familiar to the computer science guys ? Yes this is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Hashing&lt;/code&gt; ! It has wide usage from designing a HashMap, Lookup tables to creating a md5 hash for cryptographic purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/hashing.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;hashing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-why-hash-when-you-can-use-random-short-strings-&quot;&gt;But why hash when you can use random short strings ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes. This is a valid approach. The original long url would be mapped to a short sequence of random strings. One reason where hashing would have advantage over random strings is, if for some reason my database crashes and I do not have a backup then I would not be able to recover the short url even if I managed to pull the old long url (say from some other user account data, app logs etc). Hashing will guarantee me that it will reproduce the same old short url for the original url. Just a design perspective we might consider while building this app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-demo-project&quot;&gt;A demo project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us create a small &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;django project&lt;/code&gt; to uderstand how URL shortening work.
You may fork my project &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/anandjoshi91/url-shortener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;url-shortener&lt;/a&gt;  from the GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After forking the above repo, change the log path in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;shorturl/settings.py&lt;/code&gt; and run the application by typing the following command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;python manage.py runserver
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will create the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;shorturl/db.sqlite3&lt;/code&gt; file. After this run the DB migrations to create the required tables by using the following command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;python manage.py migrate
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;this-is-how-the-home-page-looks&quot;&gt;This is how the home page looks.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/url-shortener-home.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;url-shortener-home&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;compact-url-after-shortening-it&quot;&gt;Compact URL after shortening it.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/url-shorten.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;url-shorten&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heart of the project is to understand how to write a good &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eternallyconfuzzled.com/tuts/algorithms/jsw_tut_hashing.aspx&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hashing function.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us look at the the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;model.py&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; inside the smallify app in the above project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;URL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;models&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;original_url&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;models&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;CharField&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;max_length&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;300&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;unique&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shortened_url&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;models&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;CharField&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;max_length&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;unique&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;shorten_url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shortened_url&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;__fnv_hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;original_url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shortened_url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;original_url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shortened_url&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;original_url&lt;/span&gt;
        
        
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;staticmethod&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;__fnv_hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;h&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2166136261&lt;/span&gt;
        
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;h&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;16777619&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;ord&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        
        &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# Return 8 bit URL
&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;base64&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;encode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;281474976710656&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;__str__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;models&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;__str__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes use of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.isthe.com/chongo/tech/comp/fnv/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;FNV hashing algorithm&lt;/a&gt;.
Look at the private method &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;__fnv_hash&lt;/code&gt; in the above code snippet. It converts an arbitary length of string &lt;em&gt;key&lt;/em&gt; into a 8 bit URL. Here every character of the key (original url) is XORed with a random integer &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; which is also multiplied at each stage to get a good folding effect. XORing gives a good uniform distribution. After this we encode the  given integer to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Base64&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;base64&lt;/a&gt;. Like a binary base has only 2 digits to represent every possible number, base64 uses 64 different characters. This gives us a more compact representation of the integer &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;. Finally, we do modular division by &lt;em&gt;(281474976710655 + 1)&lt;/em&gt; to get a 8 bit compact URL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-281474976710656-&quot;&gt;Why 281474976710656 ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see from the below commands, the 64th character (starts with 0 to 63) is an underscore &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot; _ &quot;&lt;/code&gt;. So the value of 8 consecutive &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot; _ &quot;&lt;/code&gt; is 281474976710655 and hence we do a modular division with (281474976710655 + 1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/encoding-url-shortener.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;encoding-url-shortener&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;With this, we have some basic understanding of URL Shorteners. The demo project &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/anandjoshi91/url-shortener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;url-shortener&lt;/a&gt; in quite naive and created for this tutorial. Do check it out and let me know if you have any improvements in it. Feel free to send a pull request and looking forward to your views, opinions, and tips in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2016-10/URL-Shortening</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://anandjoshi.me/articles/2016-10/URL-Shortening</guid>
        
        <category>url shortening</category>
        
        <category>url shorteners</category>
        
        <category>geek</category>
        
        
        <category>geek</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
